Finding Aid for the Pacific Photo Club Collection LSC.0784
UCLA Library Special Collections
Pacific Photo Club Records
1900-1955
1910-1935
UCLA Library Special Collections
Bunn, George R.
Oakley, P. Benson
LSC.0784
3.6 Linear Feet (6 document boxes and 6 shoeboxes)
The records consist primarily of black-and-white photographs created by members of the Pacific Photo Club, an organization of amateur photographers active during the first three decades of the 20th century. The collection was accumulated by George R. Bunn, a member, and the majority of the photographs represent his work. Also included are club correspondence, personal correspondence, newsletters, photographic postcards, and albums representing the work of members.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942335343606533
Historical note
The Pacific Photo Club was an organization of amateur photographers across the United States active from the early 1900s through at least the 1930s. In addition to U.S. photographers, some participants hailed from Japan, Australia, and other areas.
The collection was accumulated by George R. Bunn, who lived in Los Angeles and who appears to have been an active member of the photo club.
Members corresponded by mail, exchanging photographs and assembling annotated group albums. The club also organized trips, such as camping expeditions to Yellowstone and Palm Springs, during which they practiced their avocation, and later exchanged these photos.
The Pacific Photo Club was one of many such camera and photo societies that emerged at the beginning of the 20th century for amateur photographers seeking to enhance their technique and the artistic quality of their images. A number of the photographers in this collection had their work published in amateur photography magazines, including Popular Photography and American Photography, among them E. A. Doolittle, Arthur Van W. Eltinge, C. A. Heald, J. W. Jeffers, P. Benson Oakley, G. W. Schinkel, and Elizabeth B. Wotkyns.
Other similar titles from the era include Anthony's Photographic Bulletin, The Photographic Times, The American Amateur Photographer, The Photo Beacon, Camera Notes, Camera and Darkroom, Photographic Topics, and Popular Photography.
In addition to submitting photos for publication, and in some cases commentary, subscribers to these publications would post classified-style ads requesting exchange. For example, the following appeared in American Photography, Vol. 9 (January - December 1915):
"507. George R. Bunn. 1571 W. First St., Los Angeles, Calif. 3) 4 x 5Y2 prints, all kinds D. O. P. of California mountain and marine scenery to exchange for artistic scenery preferred."
Scope and Content
The collection consists primarily of black-and-white photographs created by members of the Pacific Photo Club. The bulk of the images appear to have been taken by George R. Bunn. Also included are club correspondence, personal correspondence, newsletters, photographic postcards, and albums representing the work of members.
The majority of photographs were taken in the U.S., though some were shot in locations as far away as Japan, India, Australia, and Europe. Subjects include landscapes, people, street scenes, historic landmarks, civic events (e.g., parades, rodeos, car shows, and festivals), and artistic still lifes. The bulk of the subjects are nature related, with many photos of the American West, including national parks and forests. The images also provide insight into the fashions of the times, in particular women's hiking garb.
The albums compiled by members, with their attendant correspondence, document the procedures and function of this photo club.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 3 series.
Series 1: Photographs, 1907-1955
Subseries 1.1: Albums
Subseries 1.2: Loose photographs
Subseries 1.3: Grouped photographs
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1913-1921
Subseries 2.1 Bunn, George R.: Personal correspondence, circa 1918-1921
Subseries 2.2. Bunn, George R.: Club-related correspondence, circa 1913-1921
Series 3: Publications, 1901-1903
- Series 1: Photographs, 1907-1955; 1910-1935
  Scope and Contents note
  Photographs are mostly 3x5 or smaller, but range in size and format, including oversize prints, panoramic images, 5x7 prints, and mounted prints.
  Arrangement note
  The photographs did not appear to be in any specific order when processing began. About two-thirds of them were kept by Bunn in individual envelopes, often labeled by subject or date. These grouped photos appeared to be primarily photos that Bunn had taken himself; apparently each envelope corresponded to a roll of film. In processing this collection, the grouped photographs were kept together in order to reflect their context and respect Bunn's original order of the collection.
  About one third of the photographs were loose and not organized by subject or photographer. There were many photos by Bunn in this set, along with photos by many other club members, which suggests that these were chosen by participating club members for sharing with one another. Annotations on the back of some photos support this assumption. For example, some include a list of initials, crossed out, which corresponds with the club's practice of circulating photos among members for feedback. Since these loose photos apparently represent the club's activity (including Bunn's own selections), they were arranged separately from the rest of Bunn's photos.
  The loose photographs have been arranged by photographer in alphabetical order, when the photographer could be identified. Photographs by unidentified photographers in Box 3 have been bundled together when related by subject or photographer's handwriting.
  - Subseries 1.1: Albums, Undated, 1917-1921
    The club-related albums are three among what was presumably a much larger output, as evinced by their numbering. (Only numbers 6, 20, and 36 are in the collection.) The albums were produced by members of the club and circulated for comments by other contributors. The contributors' notes, in the form of a sewn sheaf of papers, are included in the folder. (See Scope and Content, Series 2.) The Japanese Souvenir Album consists of postcards from an unidentified source.
    - Pacific Photo Club, Sequoia Album No. 6, 1917 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Pacific Photo Club, Sequoia Album No. 20, 1919 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Pacific Photo Club, Sequoia Album No. 36, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Japanese Souvenir Album, Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Alabama, Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Bunn, George R., Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 1.2: Loose photographs, 1908-1955; 1910-1920
    Note: Color images can be found in Box 2, Folder 6 (P. Benson Oakley) and in Box 5, Folder 5 (oversize prints).
    - Andrews, J. C., Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Baldi, M., Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bastla, C. S., Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bezzi, Pietro [Miller, Oscar W.], Undated, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Biggin, H. M., Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bryer, J. D., Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bunn, George R. (1 of 9), Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Although the majority of these loose photos (Box 6, Folders 1 through 9) are not identified with Bunn's name, the subjects, handwriting, and wording of the descriptions on the back indicate that they are most likely his.
    - Bunn, George R. (2 of 9), Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Bunn, George R. (3 of 9), Undated, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Bunn, George R. (4 of 9), Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Bunn, George R. (5 of 9), Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Bunn, George R. (6 of 9), Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Bunn, George R. (7 of 9), Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Bunn, George R. (8 of 9), Undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Bunn, George R. (9 of 9), 1900-1955 (Box 9)
    - Carpenter, Harry E., Undated, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Chance, Burr E., Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Clamer, G. G., Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Clark, William H., Jr., Undated, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Cook, [E.] G., Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Doll, J. J., Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Doolittle, E. A., Undated, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Eltinge, Arthur Van W. (1 of 2), Undated, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Eltinge, Arthur Van W. (2 of 2), Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Farnsworth, Carl, Undated, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Fenton, Undated, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Ferris, H. C., Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Flint, J. C., Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - G. W., Undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Gilfillan, Archie, Undated, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Grofe, Harvey G., Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Hawkins, W. H., Undated, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Heald, C. A., Undated, 1915-1917 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Heald, J. L., Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Held, George C., Undated, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Holmes, E., Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Hoover, C.G. and Thos. B., Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Humphrey, R., 1913 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Identified photographers with single photos, Undated, 1912-1916, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Scope and Content
      Includes photographs by Lloyd C. Robinson, L. E. Whitford, Geo. W. Teasdale, W. M. Lyon, A. J. Polaski, Otto H. Granz, James Guy, and Marjorie Hunt, et. al.
    - Irving, Grace, Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - J. E. B., Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - James, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Jeffers, J. W., Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Jessup, Ray [R. H. J.], Undated, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Johnston, H. F. E., Undated, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Kiefer, J. B., Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Krinkel, H. N., Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Krückemeier, Aug, Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Leipziger Presse-Büro, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Locke, E. L., Undated, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Lowe, Undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - M. A. C., Undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Marsh, Undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Mary, Undated, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - McClure, Undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Millea, L. E., Undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Miller, Oscar W. (1 of 2), Undated, 1910-1913 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Miller, Oscar W. (2 of 2), Undated, 1906, 1909-1913 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Mizuya, Chizu, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Mounted Unknown, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Munsey, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Nicholson, George M., Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Oakley, P. Benson (1 of 2), Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Box 2 Folder 6 contains color images by Oakley.
    - Oakley, P. Benson (2 of 2), Undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Olson, Herbert, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Owsley, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Pitman, Arthur B., Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Preston, A. W. (Mrs.), Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Rice, Frank A., Undated, 1910, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Richardson, A. J., 1913, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Sadler, H. [A.], Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Seil, [N.], Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Shinkle, [G. W.], Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Smith, Ralph R., Undated, 1912, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Soderstrum, Arthur, Undated, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Speare, Bert, Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Stradford, M. T., Undated, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Swanson, J. E., Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Turner, W. S., Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Unidentified photographers (1 of 5), Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Unidentified photographers (2 of 5), Undated, 1907, 1910-1918, 1945 (Box 3)
    - Unidentified photographers (3 of 5), Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified photographers (4 of 5), Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified photographers (5 of 5), Undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Urkew, J. [R.], Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Wahlgreen, Undated, 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Warrington, A., Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Weber, P., Undated, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Wolf, W. H., Undated, 1912, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Wotkyns, Elizabeth, Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Wright, Harold A. and Karl S., Undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Zesiger, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Subseries 1.3: Grouped photographs, 1907-1937
    Grouped photographs represent photos that were housed together, primarily in envelopes, some of which were mailed to Bunn. The vast majority were not mailed, and are presumably Bunn's personal photographs as indicated by dates, subjects, and camera roll numbers. Some other photographers' images were also grouped alongside Bunn's. Those envelopes are labeled with the photographers' names, and have been sorted as dated and undated.
    General note
    Note: Some color-tinted photos are found in this subseries.
    - Undated (1 of 4) (Box 7)
    - Undated (2 of 4) (Box 8)
    - Undated (3 of 4) (Box 9)
    - Undated (4 of 4) (Box 10)
    - Dated (1 of 2), 1913-1934 (Box 9)
    - Dated (2 of 2), 1911-1938 (Box 11)
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1913-1921
  Personal and club-related correspondence sent to Bunn. Club correspondence includes the written documentation that accompanied the three annotated group albums the club members produced that are in the collection. Each album was circulated with a notebook in which members commented on each others' work. In addition, letters from the club secretary and other members regarding their joint activities form part of these notebooks.
  Also included are letters from club members to Bunn containing photographs, as part of the club's custom of exchanging images. There are two letters from the editor of Camera Craft magazine responding to questions regarding techniques and chemicals for photo development processes.
  Personal correspondence consists of holiday greetings, wedding invitations, and a high school graduation invitation.
  - Subseries 2.1: Personal Correspondence, circa 1918-1921
    - Bunn, George R., 1917-1921 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2.2: Club-related correspondence, circa 1913-1921
    - Bunn, George R.: Club-related, Undated, 1914-1923 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Bunn, George R.: Club-related with photos (1 of 2), Undated, 1915-1927 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Bunn, George R.: Club-related with photos (2 of 2), Undated, 1919, 1924, 1935 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Series 3: Publications, 1900-1925
  These are early publications from Southern California camera clubs.
  - Souvenir, 1900; Los Angeles Camera Club (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Handwritten note on the cover reads, "1st pub L.A. Camera Club"
  - Fotonotes, 1925; Southern California Camera Club. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Los Angeles Camera Club News, 1901-1903; Los Angeles Camera Club (Box 6, Folder 1)